We've talked a little bit already about project management offices and how they can help or support
the project manager.
But there are some more characteristics you need to know for your exam.
The project management office is a uniform approach for project management in that organization.
And remember PMO can exist in the whole organization.
A department of lines of business but a PMO is generally there has some control over the projects within
that domain.
Whether it's the whole company or organization or different departments or lines of business the goal
is to surprise support not surprise that's going to support the project manager.
The PMO provides organizational process assets so templates formed software things that help the project
manager do their job.
There are some different types of those though you want to be familiar with the first one is a directive.
PMO directive PMO is where the project manager is really part of the PMO.
The PMO manages and controls all projects.
So the PMO control is very high.
The PM is part of the PMO and our organisation wants to do a project or a team wants to do a project
or a stakeholder wants to do a project.
They give that project to the PMO and the PMO controls it.
That they have a uniform approach and they do everything as far as project management goes with all
projects in that organization.
Then we have what's called a controlling PMO the controlling PMO defines project governance that they
set up what the governance will be for projects so they kind of create the framework and give it to
the project managers where the PM isn't necessarily part of the PMO.
They have required templates and forms and oversight.
They define what the project management activities are.
They set communication requirements and so the PMO control is considered moderate.
It's like they give the framework and the structure to the project manager and so there is some oversight
but they're definitely not as controlling as we saw in the directive.
The next PMO is supporting a support PMO is where the PMO acts as a coach or a consultant and they can
help the project manager but they don't really control the project manager so they're more of a consultation
role.
So they're giving advice and forms and software of best practices but they're not really telling the
PM how to do the work.
So you have directive with the most control we have controlling but just a little bit less it's a little
bit more moderate control and then very low and control is the support of PMO.
All right so no those stereotypes appear most just as if you know the organisation types keep moving
forward.